[Music]
[Applause]
all right alex what's on tap for today
today we're recording how often should
you train your glutes
oh sweet it's a quick one all right
today's video is on how often
you should train your glutes and the
answer is three if you like what you saw
today
please make sure you subscribe to my
channel and make sure you hit like
and definitely comment and i'll answer
away
[Music]
all right i keyed i keyed so
the short answer is indeed three times a
week so
many of out there want a short simple
answer then that's your answer three but
the long answer is two to six and here's
the deal that's a big difference
training two times versus six times it's
a threefold discrepancy but the answer
will make sense once i explain
seven different factors that need to be
taken into consideration
in order to determine your ideal glute
training frequency
now before i delve into these seven
factors first i want to touch on the
research and anecdotes so if we look at
the literature for an answer we will see
that
in general training a muscle group twice
a week
is clearly superior to training a muscle
group once a week but
here's the deal after that there's not
much evidence in support of
higher training frequencies like
training three times a week is not
better than twice
or four or five or six is not better
than just training a muscle twice a week
when volume is equated here's the
problem with the literature
number one there's no research on glutes
in this regard
there's not a whole lot of research on
glutes in general because a lot of
researchers just don't want to deal with
glutes for obvious reasons
i've got some colleagues they're like
i'll never investigate glutes i just
don't want to be accused of anything
like
putting electrodes on someone and i'm
frustrating because it's no big deal but
to them it is and i understand it in
today's world
the other issue is what if volume wasn't
equated can the glutes
handle more volume can they can the
glutes handle more training frequency
i think they can why would that be i
don't know their architecture is unique
they're huge the biggest muscle group in
the body they do a lot of joint actions
you know they carry out different types
of hip extension exercises hip abduction
exercises and hip external rotation
exercises but just anecdotally
people can usually handle a lot of
volume with glutes
so on the flip side of the literature
we've got anecdotes how
do the people with the best glute
development train their glutes how does
the creme de la creme train well i've
been lucky enough to work with a lot of
a lot of like top 10 bikini olympians
you know i've probably worked with like
20 different
women who have placed in the top 10 for
miss bikini olympia and i have trained
so many women from around the world who
have visited me or just who have been my
clients that
that experienced incredible results and
had amazing glute development i mean i'd
venture to guess that nobody in the
world has worked with
more people with great glutes than i
have no one even comes close
and based on what i've seen i would say
that the majority of women
with amazing glute development do train
glutes three times a week some of them
twice a week and some of them up to like
six times a week but in general
three times would be the most common
glute training frequency
amongst high level bikini competitors
with nice glutes so now
we've talked about research and
anecdotes let's dive into these seven
different factors
number one is genetics now this is by
far the most important factor and i
never hear anyone talk about it i've
done a lot of research in this area and
genetics is huge and you know this if
you just have a lot of lifting partners
if you train people there's some people
that can train
a muscle all the time and just hammer it
with tons of volume
and then like the next day they're back
they're back ready to roll again they
don't get very sore
they don't experience a lot of muscle
damage on the flip side
there's people who just look at a weight
and they're sore the next day and
they're beat up and they have to take a
couple days off well what's the
difference between those two people
well one has excellent genetics for
muscle damage and repair the other does
not
and there's actually a lot of research
on this and it's fascinating but yes
some people don't experience a lot of
muscle damage and they repair quicker
than other people
so obviously people with good recovery
and damage genetics are going to be able
to train more frequently than people
without and you know if you're that type
of person you know
the second is exercise selection and
this is huge as well what if all you did
was
barbell glute bridges and lateral band
walks you could probably do those two
exercises six days a week
on the flip side what if all you did was
heavy ass deadlifts and
barbell walking lunges to failure i
would have a tough time doing those
twice a week
because my glutes would be so sore my
adductors get sore from lunges as well
but also deadlifts beat me up
systemically so do lunges like the rest
of the week i take more naps i'm just
wiped out i'm exhausted i go to sleep
earlier so what's the difference between
those two types of exercises well
glute bridges and lateral bandwalks they
don't work you hard at long muscle lanes
they also don't involve a heavy
eccentric component when you do
a deadlift you lift the weight up you
lower it down you don't dive bomb it
down
unless you kind of like let gravity pull
it down for you and drop the weight but
if you control the weight on the way
down it gets harder into the stretch so
you kind of have to go a little slow
because you're working very hard
eccentrically on the flip side a barbell
glute bridge
you know you come up you come down you
don't have to lower it under control it
gets easier as you lower it for my phd
thesis
i investigated how people typically do
squats versus hip thrusts when they do
squats while standing on a force plate
the lowering phase is only 10 percent
less than the lifting phase in other
words
during the concentric action it's only
10 percent more force than
during the eccentric action in contrast
with hip thrusts this is when you can
just slam the plates down to the ground
with hip thrusts
people only use one third of their
concentric force during the eccentric
phase meaning
they use three times more force to lift
the weight than they do to lower it
so squats lunges stiff leg deadlifts
things like that
they have more of an emphasis on the
eccentric phase
they also stretch you to longer length
and think about when you're contracting
your muscles
the muscles pull together but during an
eccentric phase they're being stretched
so that kind of is contradictory and
that's where you get more muscle damage
you know more tears more micro lesions
things like that
so during a barbell glute bridge you
don't stretch the muscle to a long
length think of a about a lateral band
walk there's not a lot of tension
you know in the stretch at all you don't
get tension until you're
abducted till the muscles that are very
short muscling so these don't create a
lot of damage you don't need to repair
if there's no damage created in the
first place then there's not a lot of
repair needed
you can train the glutes very frequently
that way the next factor is volume
if you just did four sets a day you
could probably train the glutes every
day
seven days a week now i don't like
people training seven days a week
because i think it's very important to
have one
pure rest day a week at least one you
need that psychologically so you can be
excited to set pr's and excited to train
hard but if you perform
30 sets in one day you know you're going
to be beat up
you're not going to be able to train as
frequently now some people can handle
more volume than others
because of genetics in general if you do
around 12 sets per session
most people can train around three days
a week with that and end up with around
36 sets per week
that's what i do with my booty by brad
but with booty by brett i'll throw in
additional days
where it's just little glute circuits
that don't beat you up too much
this just adds what i call penalty free
volume it doesn't hamper your recovery
but it just adds a little more volume
gives you a little bit more development
as long as you don't overdo it
the next factor is load in the
literature interestingly
and contrary to popular opinion lighter
weight
creates more muscle damage than heavier
weight now that's counterintuitive
but here's the deal that's what the
literature says in practice
heavier weight beats you up more and
here's why when you use heavy weight
your form degrades more
you know when i'm doing a one-rep max
deadlift i'm not
picture perfect i will round a little
bit my body contorts
when you have to kind of contort
yourself to lift the weight you end up
with more joint damage more damage to
other structures other than just the
muscles
and this beats you up locally and
systemically you know your body knows
when something's damaged it's going to
try to shut you down
so if you use picture perfect form it's
not as big of a deal but if you're
training really hard
you're bound to stray a little bit from
ideal form and heavy heavyweight will
probably beat you up a little bit more
than lighter weight next up we have
effort this is a huge area of concern
you see those people that go to the gym
and they just kind of like
you know they're doing like lunges and
then they stop their set and you're like
they could have done 10 more easily
they're not even training close to
failure
in contrast you have those people were
like oh my god you're watching lift
you're like they're done they're done
they can't do another more and somehow
they squeeze out like four more reps
and you're like how in the hell are they
doing that some people train with way
more effort than other people
if you train with low effort and you
just do like think about the
like the old school jane fonda like
calisthenic workouts for your butt
you can do those every day you're not
training with high effort you're not
trying to set prs
you're not utilizing progressive
overload so effort is huge here
now this next factor is similar to
effort but i i actually separate it
because it's actually something that
needs to be taken into consideration
your intention
there are some lifters who just lift
they don't set pr's they just go to the
gym and
get a good workout in there are other
lifters who are dead set on utilizing
progressive overload
i will tell you progressive overload is
a lot more daunting it's a lot more
challenging you can't train as
frequently when you're going for
progressive overload as you can when
you're not think about
you know going to the gym and not
needing to set any pr's just kind of
going for the mind muscle connection
going for the feel
squeezing trying to get a pump feel the
burn if you train that way
you could train way more frequently than
when you actually have something written
down you're like i've gotten 315 for 10
reps i'm going for 11 or 12.
big difference there and the last factor
is whether you're specializing or not my
booty by brett program for example is
like a permanent glute specialization
program yes we do full body you're going
to train your upper body as well
but the emphasis is shifted towards the
glutes now there's some research that
indicates that that when you specialize
you can handle more volume for that part
the problem with a lot of people's
programs they try to kind of specialize
in everything they try to do extra
volume for their glutes
their quads their hammies their pecs
their delts their
lats their arms it's too much when you
lessen the volume for other muscle
groups and increase the volume for one
area
you can probably handle a little bit
more training frequency so now i've gone
through the seven factors now
let me wrap things up and provide an
example so let's take a woman for
example with
very poor recovery genetics performing
the hardest exercise to recover from
like bulgarian split squats and sumo
deadlifts or something like that
doing a lot of volume per workout
incorporating heavy loads
training every set to failure focusing
on progressive overload
and hammering every body part this lady
probably can't even train the glutes
twice a week because it's
all the things that lessen your
potential glute training frequency
on the flip side take someone with
superior glute recovery genetics
performing mostly exercises that work
you at shorter muscle lengths and don't
have a heavy eccentric component like
hip
thrust and band work using medium to
high rep loads not
tanking each set to failure just going
for mind muscle connection
not really trying to set prs and someone
who specializes in the glutes it doesn't
do a ton of volume for other muscle
groups now this woman can train the
glutes six days a week no problem
okay so i just listed both extremes
chances are you're gonna be in the
middle with most of these
and you should probably train the glutes
three times a week but it might be two
times a week depending on your factors
or it could be five times a week
depending on your factors but i wanted
to give you everything to consider to
help you be as scientific with your
programming as possible to give you the
best possible chance of succeeding
all right that's a true wrap this time i
hope you like what you saw please make
sure you are subscribed to my channel
and definitely hit like if you like what
you saw and leave a comment i'm trying
my best to answer these questions i've
got a lot more in store for you
2021 is all about youtube thank you for
watching
now if this video intrigued you and you
would like to train
under my system using my principles then
i invite you to click on the link below
and subscribe to booty by brett and join
the thousands of other happy members
who are seeing amazing results
you